<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DataWave: Collaborative Gravity Wave Research on The DataWave Project</title>
    <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DataWave: Collaborative Gravity Wave Research on The DataWave Project</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://datawaveproject.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Post-Doc Position at Goethe Universität Frankfurt</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/goethe_postdoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/goethe_postdoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/Jobs/images/Goethe_square.png&#34; alt=&#34;tesr&#34; style=&#34;float:left;width:25%;height:25%;padding:0 25px 0 0;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Advisor: Prof. Dr. Ulrich Achatz &lt;/h2&gt;       
&lt;!--  --&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/pdfs/postdoc_Ulrich.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Here&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt; A 4-year post doctoral position is opening in the research group &lt;i&gt;Theory of Atmospheric Dynamics and Climate&lt;/i&gt; at the Institute of Atmospheric and Environmental Sciences of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://frankfurt.de/english/about-frankfurt&#34;&gt;Goethe University&lt;/a&gt; to be filled as soon as possible. The proposed research will deal with the theory and efficient modeling of atmospheric gravity waves. The focus will be on mountain waves in the advanced gravity wave module MS-GWaM in the UA-ICON weather and climate model.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD and PostDoc at Rice University</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/rice_phd_postdoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/rice_phd_postdoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/Jobs/images/Rice_Square.png&#34; alt=&#34;University Logo&#34; style=&#34;float:left;width:25%;height:25%;padding:0 25px 0 0;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Advisor: Pedram Hassanzadeh &lt;/h2&gt;                                           
&lt;!-- ![logo](/Jobs/images/Rice_Square.png) --&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/Rice_Ad.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Here&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pedram.rice.edu/&#34;&gt;Rice University Environmental Fluid Dynamics Group&lt;/a&gt; has one postdoc and one PhD position to work on applications of machine learning (ML) to improve the modeling and prediction of atmospheric processes, climate variability, and weather extremes. One topic of particular interest is developing new subgrid-scale parameterizations for atmospheric gravity waves by leveraging high-resolution simulations, observational data, and novel ML techniques. This project is part of two multi-disciplinary collaborative initiatives involving several US and international teams: &lt;a href=&#34;https://datawaveproject.github.io/&#34;&gt;DataWave&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cssi-gws.github.io/&#34;&gt;CSSI-GW&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Position at Stanford University School of Earth</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/stanford_phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/stanford_phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/Jobs/images/Stanford_square.png&#34; alt=&#34;tesr&#34; style=&#34;float:left;width:25%;height:25%;padding:0 25px 0 0;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Advisor: Prof. Dr. Aditi Sheshadri &lt;/h2&gt;                                           
&lt;!-- ![logo](/images/cover/Goethe_square.png) --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;a href=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/pdfs/PhD_Ulrich.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Here&lt;/a&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an opening for a PhD student to join the research group &lt;i&gt;Atmospheric dynamics, variability, and change&lt;/i&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://eddy.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;Stanford Doerr School of Sustainability.&lt;/a&gt; to be filled as soon as possible. The focus of the appointment will be to contribute to the DataWave project and the parameterization of gravity waves. &lt;a href=&#34;https://earth.stanford.edu/ess/admissions&#34;&gt;More information can be found here.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Position at Goethe Universität Frankfurt</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/goethe_phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/goethe_phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/Jobs/images/Goethe_square.png&#34; alt=&#34;tesr&#34; style=&#34;float:left;width:25%;height:25%;padding:0 25px 0 0;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Advisor: Prof. Dr. Ulrich Achatz &lt;/h2&gt;                                           
&lt;!-- ![logo](/images/cover/Goethe_square.png) --&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/pdfs/PhD_Ulrich.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF Here&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 3-year PhD student is opening in the research group &lt;i&gt;Theory of Atmospheric Dynamics and Climate&lt;/i&gt; at the Institute of Atmospheric and Environmental Sciences of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://frankfurt.de/english/about-frankfurt&#34;&gt;Goethe University&lt;/a&gt; to be filled as soon as possible. The field of research shall be the theory of the nonlinear dynamics of atmospheric gravity waves and their efficient representation in models. The focus will be on mountain waves in the advanced parameterization framework MS-GWaM in the weather-forecast and climate code UA-ICON.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Filled] Post-Doc Position at LMD/ENS (Paris) </title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/parispostdoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/jobs/parispostdoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://datawaveproject.github.io/Jobs/images/LMD_square.png&#34; alt=&#34;logo&#34; style=&#34;float:left;width:25%;height:25%;padding:0 25px 0 0;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt; Advisor: François Lott in collaboration with R. Plougonven, H. Hertzog and A. Podglagen from LMD. &lt;/h2&gt;       
&lt;!--  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt; A 2-year post doctoral position is opening at the “Laboratoire de Meteorologie Dynamique” to work on the parameterization of atmospheric gravity waves in the IPSL Climate model. The candidate will develop off-line versions of the operational subgrid scale parameterizations of gravity waves that are related to mountains (Lott and Miller 1997), convection (Lott and Guez 2013) and fronts (de la Camara and Lott 2016) and guide them with analysis field from  ECMWF.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Nudging Tendencies Depend on the Nudging Timescale Chosen in Atmospheric Models?</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/nudging_kruse/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/nudging_kruse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christopher Kruse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Julio Bacmeister, Colin Zarzycki, Vincent Larson and Katherine Thayer-Calder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022MS003024&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nudging is a ubiquitous capability of numerical weather and climate models that is widely used in a variety of applications (e.g. crude data assimilation, “intelligent” interpolation between analysis times, constraining flow in tracer advection/diffusion simulations). Here, the focus is on the momentum nudging tendencies themselves, rather than the atmospheric state that results from application of the method. The initial intent was to interpret these tendencies as a quantitative estimate of model error (net parameterization error in particular). However, it was found that nudging tendencies depend strongly on the nudging time scale chosen, which is the primary result presented here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calibration and Uncertainty Quantification of Gravity Wave Parameterization in an Intermediate Complexity Climate Model </title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/calibration_uncertainty_mansfield/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/calibration_uncertainty_mansfield/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laura Mansfield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aditi Sheshadri&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/essoar.10511598.1&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drag due to breaking atmospheric gravity waves plays a leading order role in driving the middle atmosphere circulation, but as their horizontal wavelength ranges from tens to thousands of kilometers, part of their spectrum must be parameterized in climate models. Gravity wave parameterizations prescribe a source spectrum of waves in the lower atmosphere and allow these to propagate upwards until they either dissipate or break, where they deposit drag on the large-scale flow. These parameterizations are a source of uncertainty in climate modeling which is generally not quantified. Here, we explore the uncertainty associated with a non-orographic gravity wave parameterization in a global climate model of intermediate complexity, using the Calibrate, Emulate and Sample (CES) method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Gravity Wave Parameterization Generalizes to Capture the QBO and Response to Increased CO2</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/ml_qbo_espinosa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/ml_qbo_espinosa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zachary Espinosa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aditi Sheshadri&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Gerald Cain, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edwin Gerber&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and Kevin DallaSanta&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1029/2022GL098174&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present single-column gravity wave parameterizations (GWPs) that use machine learning to emulate non-orographic gravity wave (GW) drag and demonstrate their ability to generalize out-of-sample.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of interpretable structural model errors by combining Bayesian sparse regression and data assimilation: A chaotic Kuramoto-Sivashinsky test case</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/interpretable_model_errors_mojgani/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/interpretable_model_errors_mojgani/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rambod Mojgani, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ashesh Chattopadhyay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pedram Hassanzadeh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0091282&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Models of many engineering and natural systems are imperfect. The discrepancy between the mathematical representations of a true physical system and its imperfect model is called the model error. These model errors can lead to substantial differences between the numerical solutions of the model and the state of the system, particularly in those involving nonlinear, multi-scale phenomena. Thus, there is increasing interest in reducing model errors, particularly by leveraging the rapidly growing observational data to understand their physics and sources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observed and Modeled Mountain Waves from the Surface to the Mesosphere Near the Drake Passage</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/modeled_mountain_waves_kruse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/modeled_mountain_waves_kruse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christopher G. Kruse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M. Joan Alexander&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Lars Hoffmann, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annelize van Niekerk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Inna Polichtchouk, Julio T. Bacmeister, Laura Holt, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Riwal Plougonven&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Petr Šácha, Corwin Wright, Kaoru Sato, Ryosuke Shibuya, Sonja Gisinger, Manfred Ern, Catrin I. Meyer, and Olaf Stein&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/atsc/aop/JAS-D-21-0252.1/JAS-D-21-0252.1.xml&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four state-of-the-science numerical weather prediction (NWP) models were used to perform mountain wave- (MW) resolving hind-casts over the Drake Passage of a 10-day period in 2010 with numerous observed MW cases. The Integrated Forecast System (IFS) and the Icosahedral Nonhydrostatic (ICON) model were run at Δx ≈ 9 and 13 km globally. TheWeather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model and the Met Office Unified Model (UM) were both configured with a Δx = 3 km regional domain. All domains had tops near 1 Pa (z ≈ 80 km). These deep domains allowed quantitative validation against Atmospheric InfraRed Sounder (AIRS) observations, accounting for observation time, viewing geometry, and radiative transfer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A QBO cookbook: Sensitivity of the Quasi-Biennial Oscillation to resolution, resolved waves, and parameterized gravity waves</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/qbo_sensitivity_gerber/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/qbo_sensitivity_gerber/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaim I. Garfinkel, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edwin P. Gerber&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ofer Shamir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Jian Rao, Martin Jucker, Ian White, Nathan Paldor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2021MS002568&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most prominent mode of variability in the tropical stratosphere is the quasi-biennial oscillation (QBO), characterized by easterly and westerly winds alternating sign every 14 months. Only relatively recently have comprehensive models begun to simulate a QBO spontaneously, and even in these models the representation of the QBO typically suffers from biases. Here we elucidate the sensitivities of the QBO to a wide range of model parameters, and explore how these parameters affect the QBO behavior. We expect that these results will be helpful for improving the QBO in more comprehensive models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can we improve the realism of gravity wave parameterizations by imposing sources at all altitudes in the atmosphere?</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/lott_gwp_realism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/lott_gwp_realism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B Ribstein, C Millet, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F Lott&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, A de la Cámara&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03366244&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gravity waves are fluctuations in the atmosphere (seen in the temperature, wind velocity, and pressure fields) that transport energy and momentum from their sources in the troposphere and middle atmosphere to their sinks in the middle atmosphere. This way they exert a profound influence on the global circulation. Due to their relative small spatial scales, atmospheric general circulation models do not explicitly resolve these waves, and their effects on the circulation resolved by the model need to be parameterized. Parameterizations of gravity waves generated by fronts and flow imbalances typically assume that wave sources are at a certain vertical level in the troposphere, which is easy to implement but neglects the fact that these processes can occur at all altitudes in the atmosphere. In this study, we explore to which extent parameterizations of gravity wave due to fronts and flow imbalances can be improved by allowing waves to be emitted from all model levels. Our results show evidence of modest corrections of some model biases, and a clear improvement in the parameterized gravity waves energy spectra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountain waves produced by a stratified shear flow with a boundary layer. Part III: Trapped lee waves and horizontal momentum transport</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/lott_pt_iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/lott_pt_iii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clément Soufflet, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;François Lott&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and Bruno Deremble&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03365418/&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boundary layer theory for non-hydrostatic mountain waves presented in Part II is extended to include upward propagating gravity waves and trapped lee waves. To do so, the background wind with constant shear used in Part II is smoothly curved and become constant above a &amp;ldquo;boundary-layer&amp;rdquo; height which is much larger than the inner layer scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Closed-form discovery of structural errors in models of chaotic systems by integrating Bayesian sparse regression and data assimilation</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/ashesh_pedram_bayesian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/ashesh_pedram_bayesian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rambod Mojgani, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ashesh Chattopadhyay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pedram Hassanzadeh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00546&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Models used for many important engineering and natural systems are imperfect. The discrepancy between the mathematical representations of a true physical system and its imperfect model is called the model error. These model errors can lead to substantial difference between the numerical solutions of the model and the observations of the system, particularly in those involving nonlinear, multi-scale phenomena. Thus, there is substantial interest in reducing model errors, particularly through understanding their physics and sources and leveraging the rapid growth of observational data. Here we introduce a framework named MEDIDA: Model Error Discovery with Interpretability and Data Assimilation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountain Waves Produced by a Stratified Shear Flow with a Boundary Layer. Part II: Form Drag, Wave Drag, and Transition from Downstream Sheltering to Upstream Blocking</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/lott_pt_ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/lott_pt_ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;François Lott&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Bruno Deremble, and Clément Soufflet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/atsc/78/4/JAS-D-20-0144.1.xml?tab_body=pdf&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nonhydrostatic version of the mountain flow theory presented in Part I is detailed. In the near-neutral case, the surface pressure decreases when the flow crosses the mountain to balance an increase in surface friction along the ground. This produces a form drag that can be predicted qualitatively. When stratification increases, internal waves start to control the dynamics and the drag is due to upward-propagating mountain waves as in Part I. The reflected waves nevertheless add complexity to the transition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal and Latitudinal Variability of the Gravity Wave Spectrum in the Lower Stratosphere</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/background/seasonal_latitudinal_variability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/background/seasonal_latitudinal_variability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2020JD032850&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superpressure balloon data of unprecedented coverage from Loon LLC is used to investigate the seasonal and latitudinal variability of lower stratospheric gravity waves over the entire intrinsic frequency spectrum. We show that seasonal variability in both gravity wave amplitudes and spectral slopes exist for a wide range of intrinsic frequencies and provide estimates of spectral slopes in five latitudinal regions for all four seasons, in five different frequency windows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal and Latitudinal Variability of the Gravity Wave Spectrum in the Lower Stratosphere</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/seasonal_latitudinal_variability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/publications/papers/seasonal_latitudinal_variability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors&#34;&gt;Authors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erik A. Lindgren, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aditi Sheshadri&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aurélien Podglajen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, Robert W. Carver&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/2020JD032850&#34;&gt;Read the full paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superpressure balloon data of unprecedented coverage from Loon LLC is used to investigate the seasonal and latitudinal variability of lower stratospheric gravity waves over the entire intrinsic frequency spectrum. We show that seasonal variability in both gravity wave amplitudes and spectral slopes exist for a wide range of intrinsic frequencies and provide estimates of spectral slopes in five latitudinal regions for all four seasons, in five different frequency windows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://datawaveproject.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://datawaveproject.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description>Write to us with your questions, comments, and interests.
Your Name Email Address An email address is required. Message </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
